Chungya, are you able to speak now?
청야야 이제 말 할 수 있어?
I could originally say
원래는 이렇게 말할 수 있었는데
Chungya
청야
What did you say just now?
방금 뭐라고 했어?
You said you ordered me to be killed?
나한테 죽이라고 명령했다고 했죠?
Yes
예
why?
왜?
Maybe I hold a grudge
어쩌면 난 원한을 품고 있을지도 몰라
Are you doing this out of fear of revenge?
복수가 두려워서 그러는 걸까?
I am just a servant
나는 단지 하인일 뿐이다
What on earth can you do?
도대체 당신은 무엇을 할 수 있나요?
For you, killing people is
당신에게 있어서 사람을 죽이는 것은
Is it that easy?
그렇게 쉬운가요?
This is...
이것은...
This is what we do.
이것이 우리가 하는 일입니다.
What do you mean?
무슨 뜻이에요?
In a robbery
강도 사건에서
It's murder
살인이야
No one can survive our hands
누구도 우리 손에서 살아남을 수 없어
We gathered together with about 40 brothers.
우리는 약 40명의 형제들과 함께 모였습니다.
Often on this floor
종종 이 층에
It's called a killer crocodile.
킬러 악어라고 불립니다.
(Old name for Holyul Crocodile)
(홀리율악어의 옛 이름)
Kill it!
죽여!
Just hearing the term Gangnam murderous crocodile
강남살인악어라는 말만 들어도
I was so confused that I ran away and was able to get a large sum of money.
너무 혼란스러워서 도망쳐 큰 돈을 얻었습니다.
The six-atomic bomb does not leave behind intact corpses.
6개 원자폭탄은 온전한 시체를 남기지 않습니다.
They said we should turn the dead into wandering ghosts.
죽은 사람을 떠돌이 유령으로 만들어야 한다고 하더군요.
So they extort money
그래서 그들은 돈을 갈취한다
Did you become rich in Duhyeon?
두현에서 부자가 되셨나요?
the last thing we did
우리가 마지막으로 한 일
It's a government office that returned home.
집으로 돌아온 관공서입니다.
From that official at that time
당시 그 관계자로부터
200,000 nyang of silver money
은화 20만개
I stole five boxes of gold
나는 금 다섯 상자를 훔쳤어요
Hey, dumbass.
이봐, 멍청아.
to you
당신에게
I will give you all five boxes of gold.
금 상자 다섯 개를 모두 주겠습니다.
How do you feel?
기분이 어때요?
(Others say they don't like it)
(다른 분들은 별로라고 하더군요)
Hey, dumbass.
이봐, 멍청아.
There are over 10 jars of alcohol in there.
거기에는 10병 이상의 술이 들어있습니다.
You can drink it right now
지금 바로 드셔도 됩니다
among our children
우리 아이들 중에
You're the only one who doesn't drink, right?
술 안 마시는 사람은 너뿐이잖아?
Let's do what we always do
늘 하던 대로 하자
Did you really kill all of your brothers?
정말 형제들을 다 죽였나요?
that day
그 날
let people get drunk
사람들을 취하게 놔두세요
I cut off their heads one by one
머리를 하나씩 잘랐어요
In fact, the method for the six atomic bombs was
실제로 6개의 원자폭탄을 만드는 방법은
It's the most thorough way
가장 철저한 방법이에요
Unfortunately, I made a mistake in the middle.
아쉽게도 중간에 실수를 했습니다.
Even if someone wakes up
누군가 깨어나도
It has nothing to do with me
나와는 아무 상관이 없어
Because I'm dumb
내가 멍청하니까
I can't call someone's name
나는 누군가의 이름을 부를 수 없다
The six atomic bombs were carried out by mobilizing people.
6개의 원자폭탄은 사람들을 동원해 이뤄졌습니다.
enough to kill me
나를 죽일 만큼
Hey, dumbass.
이봐, 멍청아.
Very good job
매우 잘 했어요
What if you get drunk too?
너도 취하면 어떡하지?
Those guys
그 사람들
How much do I have to drink first?
먼저 얼마나 마셔야 하나요?
'Cause they can get it all
왜냐하면 그들은 모든 것을 얻을 수 있기 때문입니다.
(What if I kill you too ?)
(내가 너도 죽이면 어떡하지 ?)
you can never do that
넌 절대 그럴 수 없어
(why?)
(왜?)
Because I'm dumb
내가 멍청하니까
Besides, alone
게다가 혼자서
So many gold and silver treasures
금은보물이 너무 많아서
What can you use it for?
무엇을 위해 사용할 수 있나요?
Even though the six atomic bombs don’t know that I’m not dumb .
6개의 원자폭탄이 내가 바보가 아니라는 사실을 모르더라도.
Still got one thing right
그래도 한 가지 맞았어
Because I live alone
혼자 살기 때문에
I didn't know what to do.
나는 무엇을 해야할지 몰랐습니다.
So, have you been pretending to be mute on purpose all this time?
그럼 그동안 일부러 벙어리인 척 한 건가요?
After being mistreated by my stepmother
새엄마에게 학대를 당한 후
I became so dumb
난 너무 멍청해졌어
After not being able to talk for so many years
몇 년 동안 말을 하지 못한 채
At some point, I started speaking.
어느 순간 나는 말을 하기 시작했다.
But when I thought about it
그런데 생각해보니
It's not bad to live dumb
멍청하게 사는 것도 나쁘지 않아
Others are not wary of you
다른 사람들은 당신을 경계하지 않습니다
You say everything in front of me
내 앞에서는 다 말하잖아
They even took pity on me
그들은 나를 불쌍히 여기기까지 했어
So at all
그래서 전혀
I decided to live like a mute
벙어리처럼 살기로 했어요
Damn it I was dumb
젠장 내가 멍청했어
Otherwise, the six atomic bombs would never have left me alive.
그렇지 않았다면 여섯 개의 원자폭탄이 나를 살려두지 못했을 것입니다.
Then why do you
그럼 너는 왜?
I think I know if they're trying to kill me
내 생각엔 그들이 나를 죽이려고 하는지 알 것 같아
While holding a knife
칼을 쥐고 있는 동안
I'm trying to nip it in the bud.
싹을 틔워보려고 합니다.
Chungya
청야
6 years ago that winter
6년 전 그해 겨울
If Chungya hadn't taken me to the Yu family,
만약 청야가 나를 유씨네 집으로 데려가지 않았더라면,
I would already be dead
나는 이미 죽었을 것이다
Since you ordered me to be killed
당신이 나에게 죽이라고 명령한 이후로
If you don't kill me
나를 죽이지 않으면
Chungya becomes dangerous
청야가 위험해진다
My life belongs to Chungya anyway.
어차피 내 인생은 청야의 것이다.
Even if you kill me right now
지금 당장 나를 죽여도
I have nothing to say
할 말이 없다
(Doohyeon government office)
(두현청)
=Prosperous Underground= =Episode 10=
=번성하는 지하= =제10화=
The six-atomic bomb kills everyone, but
6개 원자폭탄은 모두를 죽이지만
I am not a six-won bomb
나는 6원 폭탄이 아니다
I'm different from him
나는 그 사람과 달라요
Even if I die
내가 죽어도
I will never kill you
나는 결코 당신을 죽이지 않을 것입니다
You're not going to kill me?
나를 죽이지 않을 건가요?
Do you really think I'm going to kill you?
내가 정말 당신을 죽일 거라고 생각하시나요?
no
아니요
I believe that Chungya will not kill me.
나는 청야가 나를 죽이지 않을 것이라고 믿습니다.
But what does Nari plan to do?
그런데 나리는 무엇을 할 계획인가?
As soon as I got here
여기 도착하자마자
I met a lot of peasants.
나는 많은 농부들을 만났습니다.
If I kill you right away
내가 당장 널 죽이면
in a rural town
시골 마을에서
I feel like there will only be ugly rumors for no reason.
괜히 안좋은 소문만 돌게 될 것 같은 느낌이 듭니다.
I'd rather take you
차라리 당신을 데려가겠어요
If you keep it next to you, it might actually kill you.
옆에 두면 정말 죽을 수도 있어요.
I plan to say that there are many.
많다고 말씀드리고 싶습니다.
Then I can never escape death.
그러면 나는 결코 죽음을 피할 수 없습니다.
That's right
좋아요
You never know who will die first
누가 먼저 죽을지 모르잖아요
Is it difficult to kill a six-atomic bomb?
6개 원자폭탄을 죽이는 것이 어렵나요?
it is not diffcult
어렵지 않아요
The difficult thing is
어려운 점은
Killing a person without swinging a sword
칼을 휘두르지도 않고 사람을 죽이는 행위
You can commit robbery and not be judged.
강도를 범해도 심판을 받지 않을 수 있습니다.
Kill the six atomic bombs
6개의 원자폭탄을 죽여라
Don't let anyone suspect
누구도 의심하지 못하게 하세요
next
다음
You, Bae Dong-in, study writing
당신 배동인님, 글쓰기 공부하세요
As adopted son of Yuk Won Bomb
육원폭탄의 양자로
I'm inheriting the Yuk family's wealth.
나는 육가의 부를 물려받고 있다.
What can I do with that?
그걸로 무엇을 할 수 있나요?
Does Chungya have a plan?
청야는 계획이 있나요?
I don't have a plan
난 계획이 없어
you have
당신은
Chungya
청야
I wonder if I will find a way
방법을 찾을 수 있을지 궁금해요
I don't know either
나도 모르겠어요
But you make us
하지만 당신은 우리를
The ideal that drove me to the edge of a cliff
나를 벼랑 끝으로 몰아넣은 이상
One of them has to die to end.
그 중 한 명은 끝까지 죽어야 합니다.
If we are lucky and succeed
운이 좋아서 성공한다면
I like Chungya
나는 청야를 좋아한다
I will treat you as my father.
나는 당신을 내 아버지처럼 대할 것입니다.
father
아버지
please accept me
나를 받아주세요
(Mr. Yuk’s Mansion)
(육 씨의 저택)
You came
당신이 와서
please
제발
Let's go in
들어가자
at my house
내 집에서
It was somewhere like this...
이런 곳도 있었어...
How can you live in a place like this?
이런 곳에서 어떻게 살 수 있나요?
I can buy it
나는 그것을 살 수 있다
Not only can I live
살 수 있을 뿐만 아니라
You can also drink celebratory wine.
축하 와인을 마실 수도 있습니다.
I have something to say
할 말이 있어요
Kill that six-atomic bomb
그 6개 원자폭탄을 죽여라
I plan to share my wealth with you.
나는 내 재산을 당신과 공유할 계획입니다.
No... Master
아니... 선생님
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
I mean
내 말은
I can't fight as well as Jang Gui or Ryu.
나는 장귀나 류만큼 잘 싸우지 못한다.
Because I'm not as smart as you,
나는 당신만큼 똑똑하지 않기 때문에
There's nothing I know how to do
내가 어떻게 해야할지 아는 게 하나도 없어
That's right
좋아요
I don't even have the courage to kill
죽일 용기도 없어
At least
적어도
The guy called me
그 사람이 나한테 전화했어
He is a man of loyalty.
그는 충성심이 강한 사람입니다.
Master today
오늘 마스터하세요
Since I said that
내가 그 말을 한 이후로
Master also believes in me
스승님도 나를 믿어요
It means you look at me favorably
나를 호의적으로 본다는 뜻이다
I am
그래요
I sacrificed my whole life
나는 평생을 희생했다.
I will assist you, Master.
제가 도와드리겠습니다, 마스터.
good night
안녕히 주무세요
You have a deep connection with our brother-in-law.
당신은 우리 처남과 깊은 관계를 가지고 있습니다.
We also think the same way about the death penalty.
우리는 사형제도에 대해서도 같은 생각을 합니다.
good night
안녕히 주무세요
If it's false
거짓이라면
Janggwiya
장위야
bring a knife
칼을 가져와
what are you doing?
뭐하세요?
bring it
가져와
Now it's your turn
이제 당신 차례입니다
Drink it
마셔
(Jin's General Store)
(진네 잡화점)
(Chaegwan)
(채관)
(Muryujae)
(무류재)
Jinyukja
진육자
Just leave now
지금 당장 떠나세요
What's going on here?
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는 걸까요?
Please make my dream come true
내 꿈을 현실로 만들어주세요
Is it a dream?
꿈인가요?
i don't know how to do that
난 그걸 어떻게 해야할지 모르겠어요
You can
당신은 할 수 있습니다
These days, I keep
요즘 계속해서
I dream of taking your class
나는 당신의 수업을 듣는 꿈을 꿉니다.
I have a young student who is taking class with me.
저와 함께 수업을 듣는 어린 학생이 있습니다.
They say the disciple's name was Gyo Gaedong.
그 제자의 이름이 교개동이었다고 합니다.
Gaeddong comes to me after class.
수업이 끝나면 개동이가 나에게 온다.
Because he lost his head
왜냐하면 그는 머리를 잃었기 때문이다.
He asked me to find his lost head.
그는 나에게 잃어버린 머리를 찾아달라고 부탁했습니다.
Master
주인
If you killed Gyogaeddong, you killed him.
교개동을 죽였으면 그 사람을 죽인 것이다.
How do you cut off a dog's head?
개의 머리를 어떻게 자르나요?
Can I bury it in my yard?
마당에 묻어도 될까요?
This has been happening in Duhyeon for quite some time.
두현에서는 이런 일이 꽤 오래전부터 있었습니다.
It's a story that has been passed down.
전해 내려온 이야기입니다.
The people here call it Wangsungni.
이곳 사람들은 이곳을 왕성리라고 부른다.
I'm sure you remember it very well.
나는 당신이 그것을 아주 잘 기억한다고 확신합니다.
Just by listening
듣는 것만으로도
It’s a name that makes my teeth tremble
이가 떨리는 이름이군요
But it's a pity
하지만 아쉽다
Master, you will never live until then.
선생님, 그때까지 당신은 결코 살 수 없습니다.
At best, he will be imprisoned and then beheaded.
기껏해야 그는 투옥된 뒤 참수형을 당할 것이다.
But do you know what?
그런데 그거 알아요?
A criminal like you is
너 같은 범죄자는
It won't be easy even in prison.
감옥에서도 쉽지 않을 겁니다.
Getting beaten and scolded is basic.
맞고 혼나는 건 기본이다.
Those prisoners
그 죄수들
On the criminal's body
범인의 몸에
They say they also spray poop and urine.
똥이나 소변도 뿌린다고 하네요.
To the point where I think it would be better to die
차라리 죽는 게 낫다고 생각할 정도로
It will be very painful
아주 고통스러울 거에요
of course
물론
Before going to the guillotine
단두대에 가기 전에
You'll be dragged down the street
넌 길바닥으로 끌려가게 될 거야
Otherwise, everyone will come to see it.
그렇지 않으면 모두가 그것을 보러 올 것입니다.
Of course, Master's friends and acquaintances
물론 스승님의 친구나 지인들도요.
All of Master's disciples will come too.
스승님의 제자들도 모두 올 것이다.
They really want you
그들은 정말로 당신을 원해요
Shall we see him as a teacher?
선생님으로 만나볼까요?
Or should we see it as a beast?
아니면 짐승으로 봐야 할까요?
After cutting the head, the body rots within 3 days.
머리를 자르고 나면 몸은 3일 안에 썩는다.
It will become food for stray dogs.
길 잃은 개들의 먹이가 될 것입니다.
Master
주인
Gyogaeddong
교개동
I'm waiting in Gucheon
구천에서 기다리고 있어요
I am...
그래요...
I didn't kill Gaeddong on purpose.
일부러 개동을 죽인 건 아니다.
It was an accidental murder
우발적인 살인이었어
It's accidental
우연이야
It means accidental
우연한 일이라는 뜻이에요
Master's copper scale marks
마스터의 구리 스케일 마크
It was imprinted on Gyogaedtong’s bones.
교개통의 뼈에 새겨져 있었습니다.
Is it still accidental murder?
아직도 우발적 살인인가요?
Who really believes that?
누가 그걸 정말로 믿나요?
that day
그 날
after class
방과후
Gyogaeddong came back secretly.
교개동이 몰래 돌아왔다.
that is...
그건...
Gaeddong
개동
You stole one of my brushes
당신은 내 브러쉬 중 하나를 훔쳤습니다
We promised to meet and play together
만나서 같이 놀기로 약속했어요
He said he would teach me how to write from that day on.
그날부터 나에게 글쓰기를 가르쳐 주겠다고 하더군요.
He said he would bring a brush too.
붓도 가져오겠다고 하더군요.
You stole one of your teacher's brushes?
선생님의 붓 중 하나를 훔쳤나요?
I truly committed a deadly sin.
나는 정말로 치명적인 죄를 지었습니다.
no, no
아니 아니
I just hit Gaetdong with a trick.
그냥 트릭으로 갯동을 때렸어요.
Stealing things?
물건을 훔친다?
How dare you steal something?
어떻게 감히 물건을 훔치나요?
Master
주인
Try hitting it to your heart's content.
마음껏 쳐보세요.
After hitting everything
다 때린 뒤
Then you have to give me the brush.
그럼 나한테 붓을 줘야지.
How is it?
어때요?
What a mean thing!
정말 비열한 일입니다!
Such a shameless guy
이런 뻔뻔한 놈이네
That's what it's like to be a child without parents
부모 없는 아이로 산다는 건 이런 거야
What did you say just now?
방금 뭐라고 했어?
I said he was a shameless guy.
나는 그 사람이 뻔뻔한 사람이라고 말했다.
You dirty and shameful bastard
더럽고 부끄러운 놈아
A person who grew up without parents...
부모 없이 자란 사람..
Did you tell Gaeddong that he grew up without parents ?
개동이가 부모 없이 자랐다고 말했나요?
okay
좋아요
However, Gyo Gaeddong grew up without a mother from a young age.
그러나 교개동은 어려서부터 엄마 없이 자랐다.
How dare you...
어떻게 감히...
Such a mean thing
이런 못된 짓
But the dog's head is
하지만 개 머리는
Why did you cut it?
왜 잘랐어요?
I wasn't in my right mind back then either.
그땐 나도 제정신이 아니었어.
(As the day gets dark)
(날이 어두워지면서)
(I have a body)
(몸이 있어요)
(moving out of the room)
(방에서 나간다)
(Perhaps people are tricked)
(아마도 사람들이 속고 있는 것 같아요)
(I'm afraid that people will notice it's a wound)
(사람들이 상처라고 알아차릴까봐 두렵다)
(stop...)
(멈추다...)
In the end I
결국 나는
headless corpse
머리 없는 시체
I hid it behind the stage
무대뒤에 숨겨놨어
Was the head buried in the yard?
머리는 마당에 묻혔나요?
after that
이후
Gaeddong every night
매일 밤 개동
came to see me
나를 만나러 왔어요
Master, hit me more.
선생님, 더 때려주세요.
(But after that)
(하지만 그 이후에는)
(I couldn't sleep well)
(잠을 잘 못 잤어요)
(Just close your eyes)
(그냥 눈을 감아봐)
Master
주인
(Because Gyogaeddong has come)
(교개동이 왔으니까)
You should take back the whip that hit me.
나를 때린 채찍을 되찾아야 한다.
okay
좋아요
Don't do that
그러지 마세요
look at this
이거 봐요
no...
아니요...
Today I
오늘 나는
Already here...
이미 여기에...
I got hit over a hundred times.
백 번도 넘게 맞았습니다.
It's not possible
불가능해요
If not...
그렇지 않다면...
I...
나...
Don't hit me more
더 때리지 마세요
It is invalid to hit the teacher alone.
혼자서 선생님을 때리는 것은 무효입니다.
It's invalid.
유효하지 않습니다.
Hitting someone alone is invalid.
혼자 사람을 때리는 것은 무효입니다.
Master
주인
Should I report it to the government office? Or would Master embroider it himself?
관공서에 신고해야 하나요? 아니면 스승님이 직접 수를 놓을까요?
Yukjikah
어서 해봐요
please please
제발 제발
Please save me
나를 구해주세요
Meantime
그 동안에
I was also very distressed.
저도 많이 괴로웠어요.
Yukjik, please, please.
육직, 제발, 제발.
please forgive me
용서해주세요
Forgiveness should be bestowed upon Gae Ddong.
개똥이를 용서해야 합니다.
If not, I
그렇지 않다면 나는
What should I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
To admit guilt
죄책감을 인정하다
What Master did
스승님이 하신 일
Write it all down without a single lie
거짓말 하나 없이 다 적어봐
After signing with a thumbprint
지문으로 서명 후
Burn it in front of the dog poop's grave.
개똥 무덤 앞에서 태워주세요.
I guess I should also report it to the government office.
관공서에도 신고해야 할 것 같아요.
no
아니요
Don't write a memorial service
추도문을 쓰지 마세요.
I will write a memorial service.
추모글을 쓰겠습니다.
(Muryujae)
(무류재)
No... where is the grave?
아니... 무덤이 어디죠?
Before that, let me take a look.
그 전에 잠깐 살펴보겠습니다.
No, no, no.
아니, 아니.
okay
좋아요
Look
바라보다
No, you...
아니, 당신은...
Master
주인
We'll give you a ride instead.
대신 차량을 제공해 드리겠습니다.
No, what on earth are you trying to do?
아니 도대체 무슨 짓을 하려는 걸까요?
Master
주인
I changed my mind, I'm not reporting it.
마음이 바뀌어서 신고하지 않겠습니다.
So, am I doing you a favor?
그럼 내가 당신에게 호의를 베푸는 건가요?
yes
예
You are my benefactor
당신은 나의 은인입니다
If so, I would like to ask you a small favor.
그렇다면 작은 부탁 하나를 드리고 싶습니다.
Would you please listen?
좀 들어주시겠어요?
You were trying to trap me from the beginning.
당신은 처음부터 나를 함정에 빠뜨리려고 했어요.
long ear
긴 귀
Please speak well to your teacher.
선생님께 잘 말씀해주세요.
Mr. Wang
왕씨
Thank you for your hard work
당신의 노고에 감사드립니다
Now, is Rep. Jeong next?
자, 다음은 정 의원 차례인가?
Yes, that's right.
네, 맞습니다.
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
It won't be easy like Mr. Wang
왕 선생님처럼 쉽지는 않을 거예요
He is a very famous person
그는 매우 유명한 사람이다
The county governor also showed his illness to Rep. Jeong, didn’t he?
군수님도 정 의원에게 자신의 병을 보여주셨죠?
furthermore
뿐만 아니라
I just stole a few antiques.
방금 골동품 몇 개를 훔쳤어요.
ask for sin
죄를 묻다
Making them listen to us obediently
우리 말을 순종적으로 듣게 만드는 것
It won't be easy
쉽지 않을 거야
yes
예
It was already a pain in the ass
이미 골치 아픈 일이었어
Unexpectedly, King Jin
뜻밖에도 진왕이
They've already prepared everything.
그들은 이미 모든 것을 준비했습니다.
King Jin?
진왕?
What did he do?
그가 무슨 짓을 한거야?
In the beginning
처음에는
Because King Jin had a gambling debt,
진왕은 도박 빚이 있었기 때문에
Debtors came to visit me
채무자들이 나를 찾아왔다
I paid it back at that time.
그 때 갚았어요.
Then a few days later
그러다가 며칠 뒤
Just then, Rep. Jeong came by.
그때 정 의원이 찾아왔다.
I suddenly have a thought
갑자기 생각이 나네요
The fact that Rep. Jeong stole something
정 의원이 물건을 훔쳤다는 사실
Let King Jin know
진왕에게 알려주세요
Lost and found documents
분실 및 발견된 문서
I gave it to King Jin.
나는 그것을 진왕에게 주었다.
Actually, King Jin
사실 진왕은
By slandering Rep. Jeong,
정 의원을 비방해서
I was thinking of taking money from you at this point...
지금은 너한테 돈을 뺏어갈 생각이었는데...
Such a foolish guy
정말 어리석은 놈이군
That's right
좋아요
I stole it, but you can't let me see it.
내가 훔쳤는데 당신이 나한테 보여주면 안 돼요.
But King Jin, he
하지만 진왕은
He was worse than me.
그는 나보다 더 나빴습니다.
Is it evil?
악인가요?
Are you asking for more money?
돈을 더 달라고 하시나요?
That's not it
그게 아니야
I didn't ask for money
나는 돈을 요구하지 않았다
That's why it's evil.
그렇기 때문에 악한 것입니다.
You didn't ask for money?
돈 달라고 안 했어?
As I said
내가 말했듯이
Detecting Rep. Jeong’s theft
정 의원의 도난 감지
Representative Jeong signed the statement and
정 대표는 성명서에 서명하고
They even made me stamp my hand.
나한테 손도장을 찍게 하기도 하더군요.
Sore
아픈
King Jin for a few days
며칠 동안 진왕
I was lucky and didn't have gambling debt.
나는 운이 좋았고 도박 빚도 없었습니다.
So to Rep. Jeong
그럼 정 의원에게
They told me to do something else.
그들은 나에게 다른 일을 하라고 말했습니다.
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Are you going now?
지금 가시나요?
Yes, because the patient is waiting.
네, 환자가 기다리고 있으니까요.
I'll take you there
내가 거기로 데려다줄게
no
아니요
thank you
감사합니다
Come this way
이쪽으로 오세요
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Actually, I have a favor to ask.
사실, 부탁할 게 있어요.
You can speak comfortably.
편안하게 말씀하시면 됩니다.
Actually, I told you
사실 내가 말했잖아
building a tent
텐트를 짓다
I entrusted you with the work
나는 당신에게 일을 맡겼습니다.
Must be completed within 3 days
3일 이내에 완료해야 함
Sore
아픈
The workers I use
내가 사용하는 직원
Because the action is so slow
동작이 너무 느리기 때문에
As fast as possible
최대한 빨리
Completed in 4 days
4일만에 완료
If I don't meet the deadline
마감일을 지키지 못하면
It's obvious that I'll be punished
벌을 받을 게 뻔해
I hope Rep. Jeong can help me.
정 의원님이 도와주셨으면 좋겠습니다.
But...
하지만...
I don't know how to build a tent
텐트를 어떻게 치는지 모르겠어요
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Senator, all you have to do is buy me one day.
의원님, 당신이 해야 할 일은 언젠가 저를 사주는 것뿐입니다.
Maybe it's me
아마 나일지도 몰라
Today I will never be in a hospital bed
오늘은 절대로 병원 침대에 누워있지 않을 거예요
You can tell me not to come down.
내려오지 말라고 말씀하시면 됩니다.
How is it?
어때요?
yes, i will find a way
응, 내가 방법을 찾아볼게
Thank you, Senator.
감사합니다, 상원의원님.
Let's go this way.
이쪽으로 가자.
So Rep. Jeong
그래서 정 의원은
Nari’s prescription for medicine
나리의 약 처방
Added one more drug
약을 하나 더 추가했어요
Thanks to you, Nari
고마워요 나리님
You slept all day.
당신은 하루 종일 잤어요.
therefore
그러므로
King Jin once every few days
진왕은 며칠에 한 번씩
He said he went to see Rep. Jeong.
정 의원을 만나러 갔다고 하더군요.
that
저것
The crime is more serious than theft.
범죄는 절도보다 더 심각합니다.
King Jin unintentionally made things happen like this.
진왕은 본의 아니게 이런 일을 일으켰다.
But something even more horrifying happened later.
그런데 더 끔찍한 일은 나중에 일어났습니다.
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
We need to talk.
우리는 이야기를 해야 합니다.
A doctor who treats diseases
질병을 치료하는 의사
How to prescribe medication to a patient
환자에게 약을 처방하는 방법
Do you mean to just add something else?
그냥 다른 걸 추가하겠다는 뜻인가요?
Nari’s medicine is
나리의 약은
We make it all in our home pharmacy.
우리는 집 약국에서 모든 것을 만듭니다.
The owner of the pharmacy is okay.
약국 주인은 괜찮습니다.
I found out what the congressman did.
그 의원이 무슨 일을 했는지 알아봤습니다.
That again
또 그거
I told everything to our master.
나는 우리 주인에게 모든 것을 말했습니다.
What do you plan to do now?
지금은 무엇을 할 계획인가요?
No, that's...
아니, 그건...
Isn’t this what you asked me to do?
이게 당신이 나한테 하라고 한 거 아닙니까?
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
But you can't blame it on me.
하지만 그걸 나 탓으로 돌릴 수는 없어요.
When did I tell you to take medicine?
내가 언제 약 먹으라고 했나요?
Jinwang
진왕
Let's get it straight
똑바로하자
Isn’t this all what you told me to do?
당신이 나한테 하라고 한 게 이게 다 아닌가요?
When am I?
나는 언제입니까?
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
Is there any evidence?
증거가 있나요?
I have all the certificates
자격증 다 갖고 있어요
The witness who confessed to the theft by the congressman
국회의원의 절도를 자백한 증인
I still have it
아직 갖고 있어
that is...
그건...
Jinwang
진왕
So what I mean is
그래서 내 말은
This is it
이거 야
Isn't this meant to help you?
이건 당신을 돕기 위한 것 아닌가요?
But you can’t do this.
하지만 당신은 이것을 할 수 없습니다.
Isn't it?
그렇지 않나요?
no
아니요
I don't know, but
나는 모른다. 그러나
To our lawmakers
우리 국회의원들에게
If something like this happens...
이런 일이 생기면...
If a congressman does something like that
국회의원이 그런 짓을 하면
It's a felony
중죄입니다
The master said he would report it to the government office.
주인은 관공서에 보고하겠다고 하더군요.
I did some research.
나는 약간의 연구를했다.
Are you reporting it to the government office?
관공서에 신고하는 건가요?
You shouldn't do that.
그렇게 해서는 안 됩니다.
Absolutely not
절대적으로하지
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
If you really report it to the government office
정말 관공서에 신고하면
The rest of your life is
남은 인생은
I would have to stay in prison
감옥에 계속 있어야 할 텐데
furthermore
뿐만 아니라
Who is our Lord?
우리 주님은 누구십니까?
Would you really forgive Congressman easily?
정말로 국회의원을 쉽게 용서하시겠습니까?
Jinwang
진왕
please save me
저를 구해주세요
Please, please
제발 제발
I will give you money
나는 당신에게 돈을 줄 것이다
I'll give it as much as I can
줄 수 있는 만큼 드릴게요
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
wake up
깨우다
Please wake up.
일어나주세요.
Please sit down
앉으세요
actually
실제로
There is one way
방법은 하나야
What method?
어떤 방법인가요?
For this matter , I have no choice but to ask our master.
이 문제에 대해서는 우리 주인님께 여쭈어 볼 수밖에 없습니다.
You and I are sworn brothers.
당신과 나는 맹세한 형제입니다.
I'm sure you'll help me
당신이 나를 도와줄 거라고 확신해요
great
엄청난
I'll give you any amount of money
돈은 얼마든지 주겠다
Even if I lose all my money
돈을 다 잃어도
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
it's not about money
그것은 돈에 관한 것이 아니다
You're saying it's not about money?
돈 문제가 아니라고 하던가요?
no
아니요
We have nothing to do with each other
우리는 서로 아무 관련이 없습니다
We can also become sworn brothers.
우리도 의형제가 될 수 있습니다.
If you want to be related to me
나와 인연을 맺고 싶다면
They don't have to be sworn brothers.
그들은 맹세한 형제가 될 필요가 없습니다.
Our ages don't match, right?
우리 나이가 안 맞죠?
I'm not even thirty anymore
난 이제 서른도 안됐어
but
하지만
To Rep. Jeong
정 의원님께
I heard you have an only daughter.
당신에게는 외동딸이 있다고 들었습니다.
I’m seventeen this year.
저는 올해 열일곱 살이에요.
You're not married yet, right?
아직 결혼하지 않으셨죠?
How about making in-laws at this time?
이번에 시댁을 만들어보는 건 어떨까요?
This is what Gkung Gkung was all about.
이것이 바로 Gkung Gkung의 모든 것입니다.
Jinwang
진왕
What is this?
이게 뭔가요?
shameless guy
뻔뻔한 놈
How dare you say such a thing?
어떻게 감히 그런 말을 합니까?
I'm warning you
난 너에게 경고하는거야
Even if it means losing my life
목숨을 잃는다고 해도
your vain dream
너의 헛된 꿈
You know that you will never achieve it.
당신은 결코 그것을 달성하지 못할 것이라는 것을 알고 있습니다.
great
엄청난
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
is it so
그렇습니까?
If so, do whatever you want.
그렇다면 원하는 대로 하십시오.
But anyway
하지만 어쨌든
If the congressman goes to prison
국회의원이 감옥에 가면
Your beloved only daughter
사랑하는 외동딸
Would it still be a vain dream?
그래도 헛된 꿈이겠는가?
Isn't this King Jin?
진왕 아닌가요?
Cold Podu
콜드 포두
You mean cold radish?
차가운 무 말씀이신가요?
It was too hasty.
너무 성급했어요.
I'm not an easy guy to be cold.
나는 감기에 잘 걸리는 사람이 아니다.
Our plans must never be discovered
우리의 계획은 절대로 발각되어서는 안 됩니다
Do not worry
걱정 하지마
I'm just cold
난 그냥 추워서
Just tell me that Rep. Jeong stole something.
그냥 정 의원이 뭔가를 훔쳤다고 말해 보세요.
I asked Rep. Jeong to scold me.
정 의원에게 혼내달라고 부탁했다.
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Are you two friends?
두 분은 친구이신가요?
Naengpodu, what are you saying...
냉포두 무슨 소리야...
How dare I become friends with Rep. Jeong?
내가 감히 정 의원과 친구가 되겠는가?
Representative Jeong is an adult.
정 대표는 성인이다.
I am today
나는 오늘이다
I came to talk to Rep. Jeong about marriage.
정 의원님과 결혼에 관해 얘기하려고 왔습니다.
Are you talking to Rep. Jeong about your marriage?
정 의원과 결혼 얘기를 하고 있나요?
OK got it
알았어 알았어
Since you're a grown adult, you may have conversations about getting married.
당신은 성인이기 때문에 결혼에 대한 대화를 나눌 수도 있습니다.
two people's work
두 사람의 일
It's not something to argue about
논쟁할 일이 아니다
Jinwang
진왕
Congratulations in advance
미리 축하드립니다
Cold Podu
콜드 포두
Congratulations are too soon
축하는 너무 이르다
Rep. Jeong hasn’t responded yet.
정 의원은 아직 답변을 하지 않았다.
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
I'll ask you again
다시 묻겠습니다
Would you agree or not?
동의하시겠습니까, 아니면 동의하지 않으십니까?
Yes, I understand
네 이해했습니다
Rep. Jeong doesn't seem to like me very much.
정 의원은 나를 별로 좋아하지 않는 것 같다.
I won't force you any further.
더 이상 강요하지 않겠습니다.
Jinwang
진왕
There is something called fate in people’s lives, right?
사람의 삶에는 운명이라는 것이 있잖아요?
No matter how greedy you are
아무리 욕심이 많아도
It can't happen because it's not meant to be like that.
그런 일이 일어나려고 하는 것이 아니기 때문에 일어날 수 없습니다.
Isn't that right?
그렇지 않나요?
After all, couldn’t the company’s ledger get married once?
결국, 회사 원장은 결혼을 한 번도 할 수 없었던 걸까요?
Otherwise, you yourself
그렇지 않으면 당신 자신이
try hard
열심히 노력하다
Cold Podu
콜드 포두
That's a fair statement.
그것은 공정한 진술입니다.
You also said good things
좋은 말씀도 주셨네요
I'd like to buy you a drink.
나는 당신에게 음료수를 사고 싶습니다.
Would you like to accept my favor?
내 부탁을 받아들이시겠습니까?
I tried so hard to refuse
거절하려고 엄청 노력했는데
Yes, I see that you were rejected by Rep. Jeong.
네, 정 의원에게 거절당한 것으로 알고 있습니다.
Okay, let's have a drink.
알았어, 한잔하자.
yes
예
thank you
감사합니다
Today I'm going to drink until I'm drunk.
오늘은 취하도록 마실 예정이다.
Good
좋은
Cold Podu
콜드 포두
I have a thick stomach
나는 배가 두꺼워
I have something to ask you.
물어볼 게 있어요.
okay
좋아요
Wait
기다리다
I was so happy that I lost my mind for a moment.
너무 기뻐서 잠시 정신을 잃었습니다.
This marriage
이번 결혼
I agree
나는 동의한다
Father-in-law
시아버지
please accept me
나를 받아주세요
(Artisan Jeong Il-chi, matchmaker Naengmujil)
(정일치 장인, 냉무질 중매인)
Threatening me using my daughter as an excuse?
내 딸을 핑계로 삼아 위협한다고요?
It's serious.
심각해요.
Not at all
별말씀을요
I don't want to end up in prison
감옥에 갇히고 싶지 않아요
He is a person who sells his daughter to King Jin.
진왕에게 딸을 파는 인물이다.
To that kind of person
그런 사람에게
Where is fatherly love?
아버지의 사랑은 어디에 있습니까?
To deal with Rep. Jeong
정 의원을 상대하려면
We'll have to pay a lot of attention
우리는 많은 관심을 기울여야 할 것이다
Let's go
갑시다
Jinwang
진왕
You said you would be cross-examined with Representative Jeong, right?
정 의원과 대질심문을 받는다고 했죠?
So I brought you to the assemblyman.
그래서 제가 당신을 국회의원에게 데려왔습니다.
Cross-examination?
반대 심문?
The congressman coveted the Yuk family property.
의원은 육가의 재산을 탐냈다.
I was caught stealing.
나는 도둑질을 하다 붙잡혔다.
By colluding with King Jin, a servant of the Yuk family,
육씨의 신하인 진왕과 결탁하여
You tried to poison the master, right?
당신은 주인을 독살하려 했죠?
No, that's...
아니, 그건...
King Jin is framing me.
진왕이 나를 모함하고 있습니다.
King Jin, why are you pushing me so hard?
진왕님, 왜 저를 그렇게 세게 밀으시는 겁니까?
When did I push you away?
내가 언제 당신을 밀어냈나요?
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
He used his daughter as bait to collect the owner's money.
그는 주인의 돈을 모으기 위해 딸을 미끼로 이용했습니다.
It was the congressman who told me to steal it.
훔치라고 한 건 그 의원이었어요.
Otherwise, who will take care of my daughter?
그렇지 않으면 누가 내 딸을 돌보겠는가?
Would you marry a servant?
하인과 결혼하시겠습니까?
If that's the case, it's not here.
그렇다면 이곳은 아닙니다.
Let’s go to the government office and talk.
관공서에 가서 얘기하자.
Now I am a member of the congressman's
이제 나는 국회의원이다.
Affidavits, prescriptions, and even marriage letters
진술서, 처방전, 심지어 결혼 편지까지
I have it all
난 다 갖고 있어
I'm really curious what the government will do with this.
정부가 이걸 어떻게 할지 정말 궁금하네요.
Are you really trying to kill me?
정말 나를 죽이려고 하는 겁니까?
Do I have to die to feel better?
기분이 좋아지려면 죽어야 하나요?
Do you think I will feel better if I die?
내가 죽으면 기분이 나아질 것 같나요?
I can't live like this
난 이렇게 살 수 없어
Jang Gui, that’s enough.
장기, 그거면 충분해.
Stop letting me go
날 좀 그만 보내줘
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Dead or alive
죽었든 살았든
Take care of that.
조심하세요.
but
하지만
As long as the marriage certificate is in my hands
결혼증명서가 내 손에 있는 한
If the congressman dies
국회의원이 사망하면
your daughter's
당신 딸의
The mansion and property
저택과 재산
It all comes to me
다 나한테 온다
Besides, for me
게다가 나한테는
There is also Podu's testimony.
포두의 증언도 있습니다.
Do not cry
울지 마세요
Do not cry!
울지 마세요!
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
Maybe I'm in the government office
어쩌면 내가 관공서에 있을지도 몰라
What if I say I won’t report it?
신고하지 않겠다고 하면 어떻게 되나요?
And I also held a wedding ceremony for King Jin.
그리고 진왕의 결혼식도 거행했습니다.
I can convince you to slow down a bit.
조금 천천히 하라고 설득할 수 있어요.
even
심지어
It could ruin your marriage.
결혼 생활을 망칠 수도 있습니다.
What should I do?
어떻게 해야 하나요?
If so, what should I do?
그렇다면 어떻게 해야 합니까?
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원하세요?
What you did to me
당신이 나에게 무슨 짓을했는지
Please keep going
계속 해주세요
But this time, a little more clearly.
하지만 이번에는 조금 더 명확해졌습니다.
young master
젊은 주인
How is it?
어때요?
The handwriting is the same
손글씨도 똑같네
You're wrong
네가 틀렸어
where? What's wrong?
어디? 뭐가 문제 야?
Even though I
비록 내가
I'm not good at writing
나는 글을 잘 쓰지 못한다.
There is power in handwriting
손글씨에는 힘이 있다
It's like cutting it down with an axe.
도끼로 자르는 것과 같습니다.
no...
아니요...
So I wrote it like that, right?
그래서 제가 그렇게 썼죠?
look here
이봐
This is a will
이것은 유언장이다
If you are going to die soon
곧 죽을 예정이라면
I probably can't even hold a brush well.
아마 나는 붓도 잘 잡지 못할 것 같다.
look at this sentence
이 문장을 보세요
Everything is handed over to Yang Yukjik.
모든 것은 양육직에게 넘겨진다.
Anyone can see that he is full of blood.
누구든지 그가 피범벅이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
This was not written by a patient.
이 글은 환자가 쓴 것이 아닙니다.
It's closer to the ruling document of the county governor.
군지사의 판결문에 더 가깝습니다.
No... that's too difficult.
아니... 그건 너무 어려워요.
If you write like Nari
나리처럼 글을 쓴다면
They say I'm full-blooded
사람들은 내가 완전혈통이라고 하던데
But...
하지만...
If you use it hard
열심히 사용하다 보면
that...
저것...
It's not Nari's handwriting
나리 글씨가 아니네
It's not difficult
어렵지 않아요
Brother, please stay with Master a little longer.
형님, 조금만 더 스승님 곁에 있어주세요.
okay
좋아요
You must never feed your teacher.
절대로 선생님에게 밥을 주어서는 안 됩니다.
don't let me eat anything
아무것도 먹지 못하게 해주세요
After starving for so many days
며칠 동안 굶은 끝에
Someday soon I will see Nari’s handwriting
언젠가는 나리의 글씨를 볼 수 있겠지
You can follow along
따라하시면 ​​됩니다
This prescription is
이 처방은
It's your doctor's prescription.
의사의 처방입니다.
A symptom of shortness of breath
숨이 가빠지는 증상
This prescription is yours.
이 처방전은 당신 것입니다.
Because there is a lot of heat in the liver
간에 열이 많이 나기 때문에
When to wean off medication
약을 끊어야 할 때
You need to speak well to the person at the pharmacy.
약국에 있는 사람과 잘 이야기해야 합니다.
This is a drug for two people
이건 2인용 약이에요
Rep. Jeong
정 의원
If you take two drugs at the same time
두 가지 약을 동시에 복용하는 경우
All diseases disappear
모든 질병이 사라집니다
Isn't it completely cured?
완전히 치료된거 아냐?
It's like that.
그렇죠.
That's the way it is
즉,이 방법
great
엄청난
Thank you for your hard work, Senator.
노고에 감사드립니다, 의원님.
young master
젊은 주인
Here's the will
여기에 유언장이 있습니다
Prescription
처방
From today, we are separated from each other
오늘부터 우리는 헤어진다
Let's all do our own business.
우리 모두 자기 사업을 합시다.
Yes, master
알겠습니다
(Mr. Yuk’s Mansion)
(육 씨의 저택)
Hey
여기요
Look at this
이거 봐요
Is this perhaps the Yuk mansion?
아마도 Yuk 맨션일까요?
Yes that's right
네 그렇죠
But what happened?
그런데 무슨 일이 일어났나요?
The younger brother of Yuk Won-bok, the owner of this house.
이 집 주인 육원복의 남동생.
He has six muscles
그는 근육이 6개 있다
My brother told me to get together with my family.
형이 가족들과 함께 모이자고 했어요.
They sent me a letter
그들은 나에게 편지를 보냈어요
(Oh, thank you for your strength)
(아, 힘내주셔서 감사합니다)
You said I had a younger brother?
나한테 남동생이 있다고 했지?
father
아버지
Is this your uncle’s house?
여기가 삼촌 집인가요?
That's right, poor luck.
그렇군요, 운이 좋지 않군요.
From here onwards
여기부터는
It will soon be our home
곧 우리 집이 될 거야
(The fact that Yuk Won Bomb had a younger brother)
(육원밤에게 남동생이 있었다는 사실)
(even I didn't know)
(저도 몰랐어요)
(After I committed a crime a long time ago and ran away)
(오래전에 범죄를 저지르고 도망친 후)
(I knew you didn't come back)
(네가 돌아오지 않을 줄 알았어)
(Meanwhile, the six atomic bombs continue)
(그동안 6개의 원자폭탄은 계속된다)
(I was sending letters and money to my younger brother)
(나는 남동생에게 편지와 돈을 보내고 있었다)
(But)
(하지만)
(delivered directly through the guest)
(손님께 직접 전달)
(I didn't tell anyone)
(아무에게도 말하지 않았어요)
(This letter and money were given by Yuk Won-pok to his younger brother)
(육원복이 동생에게 준 편지와 돈)
(As long as my younger brother appears)
(동생이 나타나기만 하면)
(Even if the six atomic bombs kill you immediately)
(6개의 원자폭탄이 당신을 즉시 죽여도)
(Analects of Confucius) (No matter how well you manipulate your will)
(논어) (의지를 아무리 잘 조종해도)
(It's all useless)
(다 소용없어)
(Prison Grade)
(교도소급)
♪The center of the bone and the edge of the blade♪
???뼈의 중심과 칼날의 가장자리???
♪It’s sweet yet sticky♪
???달콤하면서도 끈적한데???
♪If you bite into something new and drink something old♪
???새로운 것을 먹고 오래된 것을 마시면???
♪Some cry, some sleep♪
???어떤 사람은 울고 어떤 사람은 자고???
♪We will honor the sacrifice with a full table♪
???우리는 만찬으로 희생을 기리겠습니까???
♪Only the barren hills are visible♪
???불모의 언덕만 보이는가???
♪ To the old road and clear, green, bustling city in the distance ♪
??? 저 멀리 옛길과 맑고 푸르른 분주한 도시로 ???
♪Because the fire continues, it is turning into ruins♪
???불이 계속되니까 폐허로 변해가는 걸까요???
♪The fateful prize that will feed you well♪
???배불리 먹여줄 운명의 상???
♪He looks at the fortune telling and says thank you♪
???운세를 보고 고맙다고 하더군요???
♪The false accusations written in the drunken oath and the appeal♪
???술취한 선서와 항소장에 적힌 허위사실???
♪When the wind blows, it disappears♪
???바람 불면 사라진다???
♪We will honor the sacrifice with a full table♪
???우리는 만찬으로 희생을 기리겠습니까???
♪Only the barren hills are visible♪
???불모의 언덕만 보이는가???
♪ To the old road and clear, green, bustling city in the distance ♪
??? 저 멀리 옛길과 맑고 푸르른 분주한 도시로 ???
♪Because the fire continues, it is turning into ruins♪
???불이 계속되니까 폐허로 변해가는 걸까요???